so it is a common
idea in the world that everyone wants to
be
happy and so it is easy to approach the
Buddha's teaching with the wish made
this make me
happy but what people might Overlook is
that the desire to be happy can easily
become an activity or dependent upon
activity I do this which is then in a
positive sense going to make me happy um
but those activities in their very
nature depend on all sorts of other
things that are typically not in your
control so the Buddhist teaching is actually not
so the Buddhist teaching is actually not
so much about becoming happy but about
being free from
suffering but what's the difference
anyone one one difference might be that
if I'm looking for happiness I will
actively constantly looking for
something outside of what is present now
instead of like if I'm looking to put an
end to suffering I start with what I
have meaning I'm suffering that's why
I'm looking for happiness because I'm
suffering right now so if I start to try
to put an end to suffering I will look
for what I got right now what kind of
activity I'm doing that make this
suffering possible and then I will try
to stop doing that instead of trying to
add something on top of this suffering I
try to stop it right there so the very
to be happy is actually born from
suffering we
saying well if someone look for
happiness is because it's not he's not
happy so he's suffering in a way so
rather than positively doing something
in order to become happy one can also
ask the question what is it that is
presently making making me unhappy and
then looking into the origin of that but
that obviously is going to be unpleasant
because one now has to come to terms
with the fact that one is not
happy and with the fact that the things
that are making you unhappy are
precisely the things that you don't want
to give
up the things that make you unhappy are
the things that you do not want to give
up ironically enough yeah so people so
that means that people are confused
about what is actually in their welfare
and making them happy
yes so what are the things then that one
would ordinarily assume make one happy
but that according to the dama are
actually making one
Suffer Well I was yeah I was going to
give the course example of the the Triad
sex drugs and rock and
roll but yeah those kind of coarser
things that go against the precepts are
kind of the first thing that one needs
to kind of question if they want to go
in this direction
MH so actually observing eight precepts
would be bringing about the right kind of
be bringing about the right kind of
Happiness immediately immediately your
say no no I'm asking I'm asking a
rhetorical question yeah oh I
see because again if you're approaching
the the whole question of how can I be
happy as quickly as possible would the
eight precepts be the answer
no because otherwise everybody would be
pursuing just that yeah
exactly so but then the question might
arise um so why is it that those things
that um that you think are happiness why
is it that they're suffering actually
and what is the difference between the
right kind of happiness and the
happiness that you get from those things
because you you factually get some sort
of Happiness as Buddha said um it's not
that there isn't any gratification ins
sensuality because if that were not the
case nobody would be if that were the
case nobody would be pursuing it like it
would be just obvious to any anyone that
this is not worth it but it's not like
that so it does give a factual sort of
uh satisfaction but what is the
difference between that satisfaction and the
between that satisfaction and the
happiness that you would get
from the dhama which as the Buddha said
Nana is the highest happiness yeah
so what what is the difference between
those
two so the first one
is
um drawing one's attention away
from the nature of one's experience or
or
the common thread of all all experience
um and is you investing one in that
which is dangerous or that which is
subject to judge what what if you still
don't see that taking taking yourself
away from the nature of the experience
is suffering is there a more acute
reason or or more acute difference in
the nature of uh like in and of itself
what that happiness
is the wrong happiness and the right
happiness
well the wrong happiness depends on
things in the
world such
as uh things that your senses present
for example more acutely content of
experience more acutely no more acutely
more acut still huh safy more well more
um specifically
like not being bothered no the wrong
happiness well
like not being bothered just like as a
circumstance that's factly you mean
ignorance and how would you call
that just in the in what what would be
the simplest label that you could give
to
that delusion or griefs pleas feeling oh
I see so the wrong type of
happiness because you might say um
obviously as you said there's a course
level where you're actively
pursuing uh stuff like in the world and
that that's abandoned through the
precepts like but it's it's not that
someone who gives that up already got
the right type of happiness because for
example you can be keeping the eight
precepts and still be engaging in
concentration practices that give you
the wrong type of Happiness so it's not
like things in the world in that core
sense it's the fact that it depends on
Pleasant feeling being there that's the
main problem with that type of Happiness
like it's based on what you're
feeling uhhuh whereas the the right type
of
happiness is is there regardless of what
you're feeling so that's why you
wouldn't really call it happiness I mean
in a u kind of colloquial sense you
could use that expression but the
difference is that
uh it's not it's about not being
bothered on a different level not like
circumstantially Pleasant feeling arose
M but it's even when the most unpleasant
feeling arises you're still not
bothered uhhuh so that's why the when
the SAS would say um
the liberated mind whatever feeling it
feels it feels it detached whether it's
Pleasant painful or neutral so it
doesn't say that it only feels Pleasant
feeling and that's the the main
distinction like um an ordinary person
all they know in order to the only way
they have to be at peace even if they're
not seeking external Pleasures is to
have pleasant feeling enduring if
painful feeling is enduring they cannot
be at ease
and uh no on the contrary this is when
they will be seeking Pleasant feeling in
any way it doesn't matter if like they
can be seeking Pleasant feeling through
what they think the dhama is and and
that's still wrong like because it's
still if it depends on circumstance if
it depends on things that are
impermanent such as feeling it's not the
Dum of it MH so um more acutely it's
it's uh the right happiness is not depending
uh the right happiness is not depending
on feeling anymore because as we already
clarified in that discussion about the
nature the difference between feeling
Sensations and emotions MH
um like when you think feelings are just
Sensations or something it's it's quite
um the problem is is watered down to a
great degree but if you understand
feeling is like feeling is that uh
that pressure that thing that
existential um drive or burden and you
recognize that you're subject to that no
matter what and you can't get rid of it
and you realize now that you need to
find a way to be at ease even while that
b burden is there like as Saras said all
feelings are suffering in and of
themselves and the Buddha gave this
simil of um for the nutriment of contact
or pressure he said it's like a cow that
wherever it it would lean on it would be
bidden by gnats and flies and stuff and
he says in the same way it's like we're
attacked by pressure attacked by and and
then he said whoever understands that
they understand the three feelings so
it's that existential B existential
burden that you can't get rid of it's
not just the Sensation that comes and
you sort of do this and that and get rid
of it it's like your entire being is
enclosed within it
and then the right happiness would
be where instead of like replacing it
with something else
you understand first and foremost
understanding that you're subject to
this and you don't have a say in it well
that already would if you really
understand it that would already
seriously diminish the burden because as
a Buddha said the burden is craving it's
the fact
that you know contrary to the fact that
it's obvious not in your control like
you've been doing every single your from
the day you were born and before you've
been doing everything you could to get
rid of it and yet not once have you
succeed succeeded for any um like
prolonged period of
time um in spite of that you still no
this time it will work this time I'll
get it mhm and it never does so just
understanding that this is not in your
control rightly is already
diing the burden while the feeling is
there so that's the the thing it's like
most of the time for people um finding
peace is more like well I've been eating
this really bitter food and now I just
find this you know sweet creamy ice
cream and that's the pleasant feeling
that people get from you know their
meditation and stuff like it's just
replacing the other stuff that they
would have but it's not really um making
them imperturbable so that even when
unpleasant feeling arises they won't be
bothered it's like I'll be at peace only
for as long as this Pleasant feeling
endures uhhuh and that's why it's still
suffering because you have to maintain
it yeah that's the difficulty the
ordinary conception of happiness is
dependent bound up with doing things
that need to be maintained yeah and as
you as you said just now it depends on
the world but uh yes sure but
there's we have to remember that the
Buddha also defined the world as in a
more acute manner mhm which is the five
Aggregates mhm yeah six sense bases yeah
so you if if if it depends on the five
Aggregates it obviously depends on the
world already like you know car family
house and stuff that is also within the
five Aggregates so that is the world
really mhm so if your happiness depends
on plasm
feeling in and of itself that's really
like the root of the the issue say that
Pleasant feeling is a DT painful feeling
is a deadly Pleasant feeling is should
be seen as painful yeah unpleasant
feeling should be seen as a dart yeah
and the neutral feeling as as
impermanent so yeah you should see the
pleasant feeling in and of itself not as
something not as something you find
safety in mhm it doesn't matter how
pleasant it is even if it comes from
something that seems seemingly not
external if it's coming from your
meditation for example you should still
see it at something as something that
you shouldn't rest on because to the
extent that you find safety in Pleasant
feeling you are for that very reason
making yourself unsafe the only true
type of safety or uh ease is when your
mind has been developed to the point
that even if that feeling were to go
next second it doesn't matter that
Pleasant feeling and then even if the
unpleasant feeling were to last for two
million years it doesn't matter that's
the right type of ease and again we're
talking about feelings here not
Sensations so it's that existential
burden so you realize it's quite a task
to develop yourself to the point
where that thing which is almost
automatically um the most personal kind
of uh deeply
felt U
thing is not a burden anymore while it's there
is not a burden anymore while it's there
like all of the all of the time or 99%
of the time the approach towards it
would be how do I kind of decrease the
weight of this so that it doesn't make
me suffer but that's again management
you want to see the full weight of
feeling the full weight of sickness
aging and death as we were discussing
it's not that that goes like um there's
actually the Su were Anand was uh I
think he
was bathing with the Buddha or something
in a in in the river and then he noticed
that uh he mentioned that the Buddha's
skin was already getting wrinkly and and
old and the Buddha exclaimed the verse
saying like you know you wretched Wicked
aging damn you or something like that
like look at how you make this body you
you know uh that used to be strong and
and healthy how how it deteriorates so
it means like he still recognized that
existential significance of that burden
displeasure of being subject to aging
but his mind was totally unaffected by
it that's the right level of Happiness
basically whereas like a person might
think like oh right happiness whatever I
don't care about this it's like no
that's replacing that's more like there
was U unpleasant feeling you replace it
with something else by oh no this is
this is just a you know this doesn't
exist or something like as we were
saying denying the significance of
things yes like this body is just a pile
of atoms or something it doesn't matter
if it ages or not meaning that's really
like a uh under the hood approach of you
replacing the feeling that was there in
order to find and all of that happens
because the the the dominant feel
feeling is unpleasant yeah so it's a
response to it really and
so so in that sense the right happiness
would come from Once you have been
enduring the right type of suffering
long enough that we discussed before
suffering that's there on its own now
that you were seeking it by practicing
self mortification but that you simply
stopped the cover up MH like you stopped
engaging in the cover up strategies that
that you used to
have um that suffering that arises once
you endure it long enough so that your
mind basically um comes down from that
natural tendency to want to outrun it at
any price at any like whichever way it
can uh um then the task is to understand
it to see as as you said to learn how to
see the arising of that feeling in and
of itself whether it's Pleasant
unpleasant neutral as
a unsafe like a hot cold that you don't
want to touch like you have no say in it
being there but uh you realize that if
you grab it either to get rid of it when
it's unpleasant or to you know hold on
to it when it's Pleasant that's why you
suffer yeah because then you are
basically taking up that feeling and
regarding it as yours
yeah and and
then if the unpleasant feeling lasts for
too long that's going to be a problem if
the pleasant feeling doesn't last long
enough or goes away that's going to be a
problem that's also going to be a
problem yeah so that's why you don't
want even even the most seemingly
harmless feeling of you know you've been
keeping the precepts you've been sense
restraint and that neutral feeling
as would say well it says even that you
should see as not worth leaning on you
should see it as
impermanent and this is how B comes to
see in fact in permanence yeah in
regards to those feelings not not again
like random Sensations secondary things
that don't carry any existential meaning
but with feeling that that is that uh as
Buddha said it's the converging point of
your holy existence it's like the the um
yeah it's what the DH centers around
really yeah the Buddha taught the DH to
those who feel yeah he said and also he
said those who fully understand feeling
that's basically definition of an yeah
and then not not like those who don't
feel anything anymore or something like
because you know there's this idea as
well I think we discussed it before like
bare perception or something uhhuh and
then really what what you're saying is I
will be happy by replacing all these
feelings with a blank nothingness and
then that so but see that's all of that
is just um not really seeing that the
craving was the root of the issue not
what you were feeling although there is
that there sakuta describes but his
conversation with saruta and then he
does say like how was like does It Go um
like um like it's a question about Nana
and then he says nothing is felt there
but that is seen actually as pleasurable
yeah but that is then frequently
misconstrued in the sense like I
shouldn't feel anything no but it's
actually those feelings are still there
but one dwells detached from it so in
that sense there's no longer feeling
yeah so you could say
um without getting too abstract like
yeah uh being disconnected from
feelings obviously like it's not like
nibana is something outside of your
Aggregates or something no still if it's
if you say it's Pleasant it has to be a
pleasant feeling it's not it's not going
to be something else but um it's not on
the same level where you're replacing
stuff no that's the difference so you
you achieve it by being able to fully
endure the the the burden of what's
what's actually there not what you think
should be there based on your
preconceived notions and um that's why you know the
notions and um that's why you know the
precepts and stuff just not optional
because that puts you in touch with that
suffering that you're supposed to
understand whereas if you're not keeping
that you can think all you want about
not managing feelings and enduring
feelings on the right level but your
actions are already the ways that you're
you know yeah in vain trying to run away
from yeah that's much further down so so
basically if you don't keep the precepts
you don't know what feeling is like
accurately you're not able to feel
properly because as soon as you feel you
you do something to get rid of it that's
that's what actions that break the eight
precepts automatically do they they
allow you a little sort of back door
when you can outrun feelings that arise
and you don't get to see them for what
they are so that's that's why it's so
important to to not do those things
because then um you know all the dham
practice you do you just won't be
regardless of it you won't be able to
understand that uh those feelings were
not the issue because if you were truly
developing the understanding that it's
the craving that's the issue why would
you go ahead and still give in yeah you
wouldn't so it's a
contradiction maybe we could
just like I hear many time like people
say like yeah but I I sit I focus on my
breath and then I calm my mind and then
then I can contemplate the nature of
feeling and things like that and how
like this practice actually instead of
making one able to see his mind actually
lead him away from that recognition of
sin yeah so the thing is
um you can the contemplation of
uh you people could say I'm
contemplating my feelings but the thing
is there's obviously various various
layers to feeling so you can grab like
secondary feelings that don't actually
matter for example um where you're doing
breath observation you can watch your
feelings on the level of how your breath
makes you feel or something and uh you
can be contemplating on that very
specific level like how when I'm
breathing you know if I Brea breathe
this way I feel like that if I breathe
that way it feels like that and then
that's how I'm supposedly contemplating
feelings but I assure you nobody is like
you know doing breath contemplation and
then suddenly that takes them all the
way back to question like you know
sickness aging and death it just doesn't
because you can't focus yourself in that
direction and then still keep sight of
that stuff so you might be contemplating
feeling but on a level that doesn't
really matter like you know the super
particular present moments sort of stuff
but the background of your entire
existence that you could die at any
moment that you don't have control over
this body that you know everything you
do fundamentally in this life won't
really amount to anything because you
will die anyway you won't be
contemplating those feelings because in
order to be FOC like going in that
direction would
actually destroy the calmness that you
have because it's based on ignoring
those things so if that's when actually
one um criteria that you could use for
something that's most likely the right
type of peace is like you can really go
in this direction of
contemplating death aging things that
people's meditation is usually not based
on and it would actually increase the
happiness and the the peace not like
destroy it because you know usually
people like thinking about the future is
too much like during their meditation
get stop thinking focus on the present
moment only so now imagine like you
start thinking about you know your
family members dying or something this
sort of contemplation that's going to
destroy the the happiness that you have
but if it's the right type of Peace it
will actually um disconnect you from
feelings even more it will place you in
that uh independence of feeling which is
the real uh happiness or safety you
could say
so could you say that like the people
who are because I hear this a lot as
well people yeah saying like oh I'm
calming my mind but it's it's not
actually their mind that they're calming
it's things that they're trying to calm
yeah there it it's things that they're
secondary to their mind that they're
actually caling and then like the dog is
being the Wild dog the analogy that I
always use if just you put the Wild dog
in a special
room that is only the things that will
not provoke it you take it out of that
room it's going to be exactly the same
condition as it was before so it's just
like managing manipulating and
interfering with your feelings with
these very specific feelings so that you
don't have to cope with the broader
picture of what your life is what you're
subject to um the danger of just being
born the fact that you could die uh like
it's never too late to too early to die
basically um and uh
yeah so if your
calmness see because see that's the
funny thing like even in the in
the uh like people are aware sometimes
of these contemplations of death and uh
and uh sickness and the the corpse
contemplations and stuff but how do they
do it they take it as an objects like a
like a Nita image magical image that you
focus on in your mind M and you just
keep and the whole significance and
burden of you being subject to death of
your possessions that are going to be
lost of your loved ones that you'll
never see again all that is totally just
taken off the picture and now it's just
this object of a dead corpse that I keep
repeating or or you know focusing on as
a as a quasi Mantra and uh that's why
then it could give rise to that same
again wrong kind of piece but if it's
that right contemplation of death where
you're truly
acknowledging while you're acknowledging
the size of your attachments and the
pleasures that you that you uh cherish
at the same time you're countering it
with the liability to abrupt and
immediate destruction and then if that
gives rise to peace that's that
independence from feeling that that is
actually like you you you you know like
there's no doubt that if you um there
there's nothing beyond that then this
could still disturb you yeah exactly
yeah and also that's how your
attachments come into sight in the first
place yeah right so you want to have
that other direction and attend
basically this is then yon so like like
attend from the origin that is where hes
and attachment in the other direction
come to be seen and that is the
direction which is experientially going
to be like death because in that
direction is is there is there anything
that you can take up in regard of yours
F
fundamentally yeah and and um that's
that's really the difference um you can
say the contemplation can either go in
the direction
of seeking Peace by ignoring your
liability to suffering which is that
inauthenticity that we discussed before
and all Pleasures partake of that you
you get you can get Peace by essentially
by forgetting like uh ignorance is bliss
as they say you can go in that direction
or you
can um become properly aware of that
liability to suffering not just by
thinking about it but by factually
abandoning the actions that uh are based
and and fully centered around covering
up the
liability and then when you expose
yourself to it long enough allow it to
endure don't uh distract yourself from
it and try to get rid of it by
impulse then your contemplation takes
you in the direction of uh understanding
that liability and then that's a
completely different thing because you
didn't try to take a shortcut you didn't
try to
um like it's actually the aggregate of
feeling that you understand it's not now
some secondary thing yeah like you know
it's it's kind of like
um you could say it's almost like
a how do you call those uh when you make
um like a model of a city before they
actually build it the maret yeah like a
little little sort of thing that
supposed to be a representation of the
real thing but actually it's not uhuh
that's kind of like the feelings that
people are contemplating during their
it's like a representation supposedly of
the bigger thing but it's it's not
actually like the bigger stuff you
entered your practice By ignoring it MH
so that's the difference even if it
looks to you like yeah this is the
actual City it's not yeah and for those
people who might already be established
in some sort of practice or or other one
way to find out that they're doing is
right is to stop doing that not the
precepts but but their methods and
techniques and then see if that disturbs
in mind if it does you know for a fact
that what you think the practice is is
actually uh creating this artificial
piece on the level of a maret in front
of you as you just describe it yeah and
it's um the thing is
that I don't know why like people don't
realize this is already a problem like
the fact that um I have to keep
maintaining this yeah that's it yeah
that that should be obvious enough like
you know it's
if if if it's already going away if I
stop doing it for a few weeks then
what's going to happen when you get sick
and die yeah so but there is this kind
of magical view that if I keep doing it
long enough eventually at some point
there's going to be this click where
it's never going to go away but the
thing is if you're developing the right
type of
Peace even like not all the way to
Enlightenment just um uh some amount of
t of the mind on account of virtue on
account of sensor strength and watching
your intentions and not giving into them
that's something that uh would
endure uh basically for as long as you
don't go and break the precepts so
nothing else you would need to be done
to maintain that sort of Happiness so it
does have a it is much less um palpable
in the beginning maybe but it does have
a much
more um Las
even if it's not full on like even
without the Buddha you know like were
these um atics before the Buddha who who
would also develop samadi and stuff
which you could say it's the right
already in the nature of the right type
of Happiness not concentration but uh
basically immovability of the mind and
then um that's already that would they
would already have that ability to uh be
at ease with a having to constantly
engage in two hours of something every
day uh because it's it's basically
depending on
you not engaging with those things that
disturb the mind yeah rather than having
to do things in order to make your mind
peaceful not not doing things that
distract you from your liability to
suffering yeah would sustain that peace
because it is basically the liability to
suffering
is the reason for you being at
peace that's the
counterintuitive nature of the liability
to suffering is the reason why you
withdraw peace yeah if that suffering
has been understood correctly and you're
not craving for or against it yeah so
the liability to suffering reminds you
if you have understood it rightly
reminds you of The Liberation from it
which is the same as saying that all the
four noble truths they basically it's
one thing like yeah that cannot be the
Noble Truth of suffering without at the
same time knowing its origin ex and its
sensation ex so if you know this is
suffering really you are already
experiencing The Liberation from it yeah
because because without being liberated
from it you would not be able to see the
totality of what is yeah exactly exactly
so it's it's mutually sustaining The
Liberation and the recognition of what
suffering is so again that's very
different from saying that you get rid
of it or something it's still there but
the fact that you understand it means
that it
can't like craving can only exist when
there is ignorance mhm and ignorance is
not some magical uh energy it's not
understanding feelings you could say not
understanding their extent not
understanding their magnitude not being
able to see them for what they are while
they endure that's the that's what
ignorance and just that you don't need to then
and just that you don't need to then
decide or or have some like accident
where oh crap then I was ignorance and
then something else happened and then I
started craving against it no the
presence of ignorance is the presence of
craving immediately so not knowing feel
not knowing feelings means craving
immediately so at the same time the
opposite applies knowing feelings
knowing their
impermanence knowing that all of them
are suffering even if they're
Pleasant that at the same time means
there's no room for craving there so
that should be your standard how do I
know whether I have been cultivating the
true freedom from craving well is it
enough when uh feeling is there no
matter it's kind I didn't manage it I
didn't try to get rid of it is it enough
for me just to know the nature of that
feeling in order to be completely
unaffected by it without having to go
through some secondary emotions that's
how you would know whether you're
getting closer to it or
not maybe going back a little bit on
what you were saying like when you say
if someone really recognize this is
suffering he experienced the already The
Liberation from it I think that's the
difficulty because I can say yeah all of
that is impermanence this is suffering
but actually if I don't experience The
Liberation from it is because I don't
see it for what it is really so it's
very easy like to fool one to fool
himself about that because yeah yeah
like if someone really recognize
something I mean if someone for example
is smoking and you really see that is
very unbeneficial from it MH he give it
up right away you don't have to wait
some like medicine or some I don't know
doing some sport or something around it
in order to understand that but that's
very yeah I think there is like quite
to say quite
some it's very easy to to see to to
think like oh I understand this is
suffering but actually not the thing is
yeah so that's one of the um that's why
there's this idea of oh I recognize a
suffering and then I have to let go of
it but the thing is that's that's
already on the level of management uh if
like what for you in that context
letting go with mean how do I replace
this even if you call it uh
contemplation even if you call it dhama
it's still replacement it's still
management so the right recognition of this is
so the right recognition of this is
suffering if it's done on the right
level it should be immediately give rise
to anata to this is not mine to letting
go to disappropriate it shouldn't take
like an extra step like you should see
it on the level of I can't Sim
simultaneously know this is suffering
and keep holding on to it if if it feels
like that then that's that recognition
of this is suffering is
insufficient and it's
um most of the time that would be that
recognition of this is suffering would
just be on the level of this is
unpleasant it wouldn't be the
recognition of that extends even to
Pleasant feelings for example that's
that much more fundamental recognition
of
uh unsafety even if it's Pleasant it's
unsafe because as soon as you touch it
like by accepting it you accept
everything that it could become later by
accepting it you accept the pain that it
could become later and if you recognize
it in that way you don't have to then
let go of it like that recognition is
the letting go of it that's why the
Buddha said if you see the first Noble
Truth whoever sees the first Noble Truth
sees all the other three whoever sees
the second Noble Truth sees all the
other three whoever sees the third sees
all the other three and so on
so um yeah it's just not
uh the general problem is is
underestimating the depth of what those
truths actually are and thinking it's
like something we already know or
something like when you would you would
think uh oh yeah we already know what's
up is or something but not really not
according to this at least so
least so
um is there anything
that could um
is there anything that could
undermine that right type of
happiness is there anything that can
undermine that right kind of Happiness
well no that's precisely why it's
right but if we're talking about um
let's say Sami which would also be considered
say Sami which would also be considered
one of the right types of happiness is
there anything that could undermine that
oh
uhhuh well breaking the precepts or I
mean I guess on the level of some a
would be it could be things more subtle
than that giving into mental intentions
yeah just yeah kind
just yeah kind
of taking that pressure that you're
already sort of withdrawn from
and kind of letting yourself be
pressured by it your habits like giving
into the habits of so the reason why I'm
saying that is because then you know
there's there would usually be the
assumption that okay you get the right
type of Happiness through your
absorption practice and then there are
like things in the world that can
disturb it like you know there's too
much noise around or something and then
that disturb you and brings you back but
even with that uh Joy
of uh zadi which is not permanent it's a
temporary Liberation as is to say well
even that is much more permanent from a
certain point of view that that the the
joy of uh meditation techniques that
people would get because it's uh it's
also the reason why it leads to full
understanding inevitably is because it's
also not on the level of just a feeling
that comes up even that is already an
understanding of feelings that's why
there is that verse in the DAP that says
there is no J for one who doesn't have
understanding and there is no
understanding for one who doesn't have J
so like this whole idea that samata is
just or Sam is like this um you can have
Sam just by doing these
exercises and and mantras without any
discernment and then that's like a
separate thing from the basana that's
completely noted by the suas so even the
pleasure of of samadi it would depend on
you already being independent of
feelings to a great degree and that's
why if someone has experienced that
pleasure that right type of pleasure
they basically have already developed
their minds even Beyond what's necessary
for becoming sa for extreme entry
because sa wouldn't have J yeah so
doesn't stickly speaking depend on being
in J and and many s with describe how a
so would be striving to get the Jas not
before that so um that's why if you get
that right piece and you're not a
so then it's not the
right because um it has to lead in that
direction like if you were already able
to make yourself independent of feelings
to the point when you where you entered
the first
J you basically already if you already
knew the Buddhist teaching you you
basically like already understood the
whole point of of the of the Mind
development M you already understood how
to disconnect yourself from feelings how
to see the
um uh yeah that somebody then would not
be a sop that's kind inconceivable yeah
yeah obviously if you haven't heard
about craving well the and and so on
well the let's say Beast that would be
there you would still to some extent
have a notion of this is mine mhm uh but
which was then the case when the Buddha
was learning yeah material and IM
material attainments but now with the
Buddhist teaching being present yeah
that's highly unlikely like if just I
mean the vast majority of people who
have put enough effort to have a
consistent meditation practice or dhama
practice to the point where they would
even think that they go Janna whether it
is the actual Jan or not there's no way
that they didn't get enough information
about the dhma m so that if it were the
actual J they wouldn't have seen the
principle of uh feelings and how to be
independent of them MH so that's why
that that right type of pleasure as it
would have said it should be cultivated
it should be sought after because it's
not even that is already not uh just
something that comes up like
circumstantially that's why it can't
happen accidentally
it's entirely based on uh
understanding the U nature of your
experience on a certain level not all
the way to Four Noble Truths but let's
say 99% of the way yeah sign of the
mindel yes yeah sign of the Mind exactly
so and what is the Mind feeling and
perception so if you haven't been able
to see that liability to suffering that
we're talking about and you're still
just preoccupied with covering it up
it's impossible possible that you would
be able to get J because that
already requires you to to be able to
feel and be unmoved by what you feel
from the mentally yeah for